Van den Haag, Ernest; Papers apap135
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Publications, 1949-2000; 2; 7.49 cubic ft.
  - Unnumbered, 1960-1998; 2.2; 0.33 cubic ft.
    - "Exchange: Arguing About Capital Punishment", Criminal Justice Ethics, 1997 Summer-Fall (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 42)
    - "Shades of Gray", Letter to the Editor on "Marxism as Farce", The New Criterion, 1998 September (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 43)
  - Unpublished Writings, 1949-1995; 2.3; 0.66 cubic ft.
    This subseries contains the unpublished writings of van den Haag. Approximately half are dated. The dated writings are arranged chronologically within the series while undated writings are arranged alphabetically by title with untitled writings at the end arranged alphabetically by subject. The writings within this subseries were identified as unpublished either because of Van den Haag's title on the folder or because they contained no identifying publication information.
    Arranged chronologically and alphabetically thereafter.
    - "Some Notes on Family and Sex Patterns in Italy", 1949 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 44)
    - "Some Notes on Family and Sex Patterns in Italy", 1949 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 45)
    - "A Note of My Views on Segregation", 1963 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 46)
    - Quotes, 1964 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 47)
    - "Individual War Crimes: Definitions and Causes", 1973 July (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 48)
    - "Discrimination and the Death Penalty", 1984 July 18 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 49)
    - Letters to the Editor, 1985-1989 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 50)
    - "A Lottery Could Help Reward Honesty and Reduce Bond Interest", 1985 March 27 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 51)
    - Untitled, Death Penalty, 1985 May 17 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 52)
    - "On Discretion in Sentencing", 1985 July 02 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 53)
    - "Legalize Drugs?", 1985 September 18 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 54)
    - Review of "The Economist's View of the World" by Steven E. Rhoads, 1985 October 02 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 55)
    - "Prostitution", 1985 November 04 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 56)
    - Untitled, On Crime and Juveniles, 1985 December 07 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 57)
    - "Active and Passive Containment", 1985 December 19 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 58)
    - "Our Role In South Africa", 1985 December 19 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 59)
    - "The Gramm Rudman Ten Percent Weight Loss Diet", 1986 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 60)
    - Introduction to Sally Reed Book, 1986 February 05 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 61)
    - "Is Capitalism Conservative?", 1986 March 25 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 62)
    - "The Phallic Style", 1986 April 27 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 63)
    - "Moral and Political Dilemmas of Abortion", and "Honesty on Prayer in Schools", 1986 June 06 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 64)
    - "Foreign Aid Anyone?", 1986 October 03 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 65)
    - Preface to "Vengeance: The Fight Against Injustice" by Graeme Neuman, 1986 November 14 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 66)
    - "Freedom and Social Justice: The Negative Definition", 1987 June 03 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 67)
    - "Are Prisons Too Costly?", 1987 November 29 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 68)
    - "Are We Deadbeats, Chumps - or Practical?", 1987 December 06 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 69)
    - A Strategy Vis A Vis The Soviet Problem", 1988 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 70)
    - Response to "The Unavoidability of Natural Law and Rights" by Tibor Machan, 1988 March 14 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 71)
    - "Sex and the Media", 1988 January 26 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 72)
    - "Government Waste: A Modest Proposal", 1988 December 30 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 73)
    - "A Word for Yonkers", 1989 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 74)
    - "Aids and Politics", 1989 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 75)
    - Untitled, Andrew Sullivan and Homosexual Marriage, 1989 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 76)
    - "Democratic Government and Art", 1989 September 25 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 77)
    - "Leadership?", 1990 March 23 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 78)
    - "Why Does Our Government Make People Homeless?", 1990 March 23 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 79)
    - "Addiction: Question and Answers", 1990 May 11 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 80)
    - "Redivivus: Erhard Redux", Soviet Union Economy, 1991 September 27 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 81)
    - "Psychiatry in Court", 1992 January 14 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 82)
    - "Varieties of Suicide", 1992 February 17 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 83)
    - "From Liberties to Entitlements", 1993 March 22 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 84)
    - "Should Illegal Drugs be Legalized?", 1993 June 29 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 85)
    - "The Denunciatory Purpose of Incarceration", 1995 (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 86)
    - "A Flash in the Pan?", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 87)
    - "A Note on the Closed Shop", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 88)
    - "Black Studies: A Reappraisal", Co-authored with Alan Reynolds, Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 89)
    - "The Case Against Public Housing", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 90)
    - "Counter Speculation and the Brennan Plan", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 91)
    - Discrimination by Judges and Juries, Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 92)
    - "Foreign Aid", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 93)
    - "The Gap Between Rich and Poor", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 94)
    - "Gorbachev: An Interim Balance", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 95)
    - "Hiring and Firing at Will", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 96)
    - "How to Reunify Germany", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 97)
    - "If Men Were Angels", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 98)
    - "Jealousy, Sex, and Love", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 99)
    - "Juveniles and the Law", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 100)
    - "Knowledge, Wisdom and the Universities", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 101)
    - "Let's Drop Prejudice Against Prejudice: How to Hate Your Neighbor", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 102)
    - "Mass Communications Research: Toward a Broader Conception", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 103)
    - "Marginal Analysis", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 104)
    - "Mario and the Death Penalty", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 105)
    - "Minimum Wage Legislation: Some Objectives and Some Effects, Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 106)
    - "A Misconceived Controversy", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 107)
    - "Natural Law and Natural Rights", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 108)
    - "The One-Party Democracy", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 109)
    - "On the Analysis of Mass Culture", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 110)
    - "On What Grounds are Social Theories Accepted?", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 111)
    - "Prognosis in Schizophrenia", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 112)
    - Review of "Science in the Cause of Man" by Gerard Piel, Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 113)
    - "Some Hypothesis About Incidence of Syndromes and Analysts", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 114)
    - "What Do We Hope to Achieve by Punishing Criminals?", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 115)
    - "Why Capital Punishment?", Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 116)
    - Untitled, Affirmative Action, Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 117)
    - Untitled, Death Penalty Abolitionists, Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 118)
    - Untitled, Karl Marx, Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 119)
    - Untitled, Social Science Educators, Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 120)
    - Xenophobia and the Threat of Personality Disintegration, Undated (Box 7 (2-Publications), Folder 121)
  - References, 1969-1990; 2.4; 0.33 cubic ft.
    This subseries contains references to van den Haag from various publications. Ernest van den Haag collected any references to himself that he found or which were sent to him. These references are in the form of news clippings, photocopies, and clipped portions of articles. These references were arranged by van den Haag chronologically and in some cases folders are also titled such as "1985, Smoking". These titled folders are arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - References, 1969-1984 (Box 8 (2-Publications), Folder 1)
    - References, 1985 (Box 8 (2-Publications), Folder 2)
    - Death Penalty, 1985 (Box 8 (2-Publications), Folder 3)
    - Smoking, 1985 (Box 8 (2-Publications), Folder 4)
    - References, 1986 (Box 8 (2-Publications), Folder 5)
    - Death Penalty, 1986 (Box 8 (2-Publications), Folder 6)
    - References, 1990 (Box 8 (2-Publications), Folder 7)
- Court Testimony, 1960-1991; 3; 1 cubic foot and 1 audiotape
  This series contains photocopies of court transcripts and bills on cases before local, state, federal, and international courts. Ernest van den Haag was called upon to testify as an expert witness before the U.S. House and Senate subcommittees and the U.S. Supreme Court between 1960 and 1973 in cases that involved desegregation. His testimony was also used at the International Court of Justice at The Hague concerning South West African relations with Ethiopia and Liberia in 1966. Ernest van den Haag's testimony in two pornography cases reveals the struggle between towns and theaters showing adult films in the early 1980s. Other topics van den Haag testified on include medicine, psychology, labor, and homosexuality. Some of the material gathered in this series also includes proposed outlines for testimony, questions to be asked, preliminary notes, and van den Haag's curriculum vitae. Expert testimony usually begins with van den Haag presenting himself by answering questions about his knowledge and background that established him as an expert on the subject.
  The series includes an audiotape likely produced by FCC officials for other FCC officials and/or consultants such as van den Haag. There is no introduction to the contents or authors of the cassette and it begins with the voice of an unidentified narrator. The recording contains narrated comments between excerpts from the Neil Rogers Show, a radio talk show from Miami. The narrator apparently felt that the show had violated an FCC decision.
  - Boutilier v. U.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service, Homosexuality Case, U.S. Supreme Court, 1966 October (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 1)
  - City of Renton v. Playtime Theaters, U.S. Supreme Court, State of Washington and U.S. Supreme Court, 1983-1986 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 2)
  - Cooper v. Mitchell Brother's Santa Ana Theater, U.S. Supreme Court, 1980-1982 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 3)
  - Desegregation Cases, 1960 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 4)
  - Desegregation Cases, 1963 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 5)
  - Desegregation Cases, 1965 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 6)
  - Desegregation Cases, 1966-1968 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 7)
  - Desegregation Cases, 1970 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 8)
  - Desegregation Cases, 1973; 2 folders (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 9-10)
  - Elkholy v. Sarasota Palms and Aslanian, Sarasota County, FL, 1989-1991 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 11)
  - Elkholy v. Sarasota Palms and Aslanian, Sarasota County, FL, Medical Charts, 1989 January (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 12)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission v. International Brotherhood of Electric Workers, et al. U.S. District Court, Southern District of NY, 1990 April (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 13)
  - Psychological Examination, Dallas, TX, 1983 November 04 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 14)
  - Southwest Africa Cases, International Court of Justice, The Hague, 1965 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 15)
  - U.S. House of Representatives, Subcommittee on Education, Emergency School Aid Act of 1970, 1970 June-1970 July (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 16)
  - U.S. House of Representatives, Subcommittee on Africa, U.S.-South African Relations, 1966 March 23; 1996 August 08 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 17)
  - U.S. Parole Commission, 1978 December 07 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 18)
  - U.S. Senate, Subcommittee on Children and Youth, Day Care Centers, 1972 March 27 (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 19)
  - U.S. Senate, Subcommittee on Criminal Laws and Procedures, Criminal Code Reform Act, 1977 June (Box 1 (3-Court Testimony), Folder 20)
  - Neil Rogers on WZTA-FM, ca. 1990-2000 (Cassette 1)
- Correspondence, 1952-2000; 4; 0.20 cubic ft.
  This series contains correspondence arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each folder. An interesting group of van den Haag's earliest correspondence includes letters written to professors at Duke and Harvard Universities proposing an experiment on animals to prove his theory of deterrence as a learned behavior. Some of his correspondence involves his duties at Fordham University between 1981 and 1983. Much of van den Haag's correspondence was about his publications and therefore can be found within the publication folders in Series 2.
  - Fordham University, General, 1981-1983 (Box 1 (4-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Fordham University, Received, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (4-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Fordham University, Sent, 1981-1983 (Box 1 (4-Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - General, 1962-2000 (Box 1 (4-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Personal, 1992-1999 (Box 1 (4-Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - Proposed Experiments, 1952-1953 (Box 1 (4-Correspondence), Folder 6)
- Research, 1968-1996; 5; 0.33 cubic ft.
  This series contains topical files on van den Haag's research in such areas as law, crime, capital punishment, and employment.
  - Capital Punishment, 1989-1996 (Box 1 (5-Research), Folder 1)
  - Employment, 1986-1989 (Box 1 (5-Research), Folder 2)
  - Law, Crime, and Punishment, 1968-1978 (Box 1 (5-Research), Folder 3)
  - Law, Crime, and Punishment, 1981-1996 (Box 1 (5-Research), Folder 4)
- Academic, 1935-1997; 6; 2.10 cubic ft.
  - New School Lecture Notes, 1935-1981; 6.1; 1.60 cubic ft.
    This subseries contains lecture notes handwritten by Ernest van den Haag on yellow legal size paper. This paper is very acidic and brittle. Van den Haag lectured on sociology and psychology while at the New School for Social Research from 1953 to 1980. The courses include Philosophy of Personality, The Individual in Crisis, and Popular Culture. his lectures touched on many topics in social science including democracy, postulates, and many aspects of American culture. Some materials contained in this subseries were collected in the years leading up to his lecture career including the 1930s and 1940s, but most of the lecture material is from the early 1950s through 1981.
    - Actors, Undated (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 1)
    - American Culture, 1952-1958 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 2)
    - American Gregariousness, Undated (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 3)
    - American Values, Undated (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 4)
    - Civilization, 1951-1954 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 5)
    - Democracy, 1953-1955 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 6)
    - Democracy, 1953-1955 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 7)
    - Equality, 1952 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 8)
    - Europe and America, 1951-1958 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 9)
    - Freedom, 1951-1956 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 10)
    - Group Psychology, Undated (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 11)
    - Labor Unions, 1977-1979 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 12)
    - Organization of Society, Undated (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 13)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1953-1963 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 14)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1958-1981 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 15)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1959-1979 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 16)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1962-1963 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 17)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 18)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1963-1972 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 19)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1963-1972 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 20)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1963-1978 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 21)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1964-1968 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 22)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1964-1974 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 23)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1966-1975 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 24)
    - Philosophy of Personality, 1971-1972 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 25)
    - Philosophy of Personality, Love, 1955 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 26)
    - Popular Culture, 1953-1958 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 27)
    - Postulates, 1946-1951; 3 folders (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 28-30)
    - Purpose of Life, Undated (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 31)
    - Revolt of the Masses, 1952-1953 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 32)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1944-1948 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 33)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1951-1971 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 34)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1952; 2 folders (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 35-36)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1952-1953 (Box 1 (6-Academic), Folder 37)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1952-1965 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 1)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1952-1969 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 2)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1953 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 3)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1953-1971 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 4)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1954 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 5)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1954-1957 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 6)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1954-1964 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 7)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1954-1971 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 8)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1954-1978 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 9)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1955-1966 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 10)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1956-1972 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 11)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1962-1973 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 12)
    - The Individual In Crisis, 1964-1967 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 13)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Art, 1954 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 14)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Advertising, 1952-1959 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 15)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Detectives, 1952-1957 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 16)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Fashion, 1954 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 17)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Kerovac, 1968 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 18)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Leisure, 1959-1964 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 19)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Movies, 1952-1961 (Box 2 (6-Academic), Folder 20)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Pop Culture, 1952 (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 1)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Pop Culture Comics, 1952-1959 (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 2)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Race, 1935-1938 (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 3)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Religion, 1951-1963 (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 4)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Science Fiction, 1958-1959 (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 5)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Sports, 1952 (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 6)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Success, 1953-1967 (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 7)
    - The Individual In Crisis, Television, 1956 (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 8)
    - The Individual In Crisis, The New Yorker, 1954-1958 (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 9)
    - The Individual In Crisis, The Western Hero, 1953-1956 (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 10)
    - Tradition and Dignity, Undated (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 11)
    - Untitled Notes, Undated (Box 3 (6-Academic), Folder 12)
  - New York University School of Law, 1993-1997; 6.2; 0.33 cubic ft.
    This subseries contains readings from 1993-1997 authored by professors from various universities addressed to members of colloquiums at New York University School of Law. These readings are entitled Colloquium on Constitutional Theory and Colloquium on the Study of Law, Philosophy, and Social Theory. These readings are arranged alphabetically by title and chronologically thereafter by semester and year. It is not clear what role van den Haag had in these colloquiums, but at this time, he was Adjunct Professor of Social Philosophy at the New York University School of Law.
    - Colloquium on Constitutional Theory, 1996 Spring (Box 4 (6-Academic), Folder 1)
    - Colloquium on Constitutional Theory, 1997 Spring (Box 4 (6-Academic), Folder 2)
    - Program for the Study of Law, Philosophy and Social Theory, 1993 Fall (Box 4 (6-Academic), Folder 3)
    - Program for the Study of Law, Philosophy and Social Theory, 1994 Fall (Box 4 (6-Academic), Folder 4)
    - Program for the Study of Law, Philosophy and Social Theory, 1995 Fall (Box 4 (6-Academic), Folder 5)
    - Program for the Study of Law, Philosophy and Social Theory, 1996 Fall; 2 folders (Box 4 (6-Academic), Folder 6-7)
    - Program for the Study of Law, Philosophy and Social Theory, 1997 Fall; 2 folders (Box 4 (6-Academic), Folder 8-9)
  - Fordham University, 1982-1986; 6.3; 0.17 cubic ft.
    This subseries contains some documents related to van den Haag's position as John M. Olin Professor of Jurisprudence and Public Policy at Fordham University from 1982-1988. There is a Fordham Bulletin, course descriptions and schedules, and grant contract expenditure reports. The Olin Lecture material is correspondence related to van den Haag's duties in setting up a speaker for the John M. Olin Lecture in 1983.
    - Bulletin, 1985-1986 (Box 5 (6-Academic), Folder 1)
    - Course Descriptions and Schedules, 1982-1984 (Box 5 (6-Academic), Folder 2)
    - Grant Contract Expenditure Reports, 1983-1984 (Box 5 (6-Academic), Folder 3)
    - Olin Lecture, "Feminism and the Family", Address Delivered by Midge Decter, Fordham University, New York City, NY, 1983 October 31 (Box 5 (6-Academic), Folder 4)
- Conferences and Meetings, 1947-1999; 7; 0.33 cubic ft.
  This series contains brochures, invitations, and documents related to conferences and meetings that Ernest van den Haag attended. There is one conference invitation from 1949 that lists van den Haag as a speaker, but the bulk of the brochures cover the 1960s forward. Van den Haag attended and spoke at several gatherings. There is one file containing speech drafts and correspondence from a conference in 1965, but the majority of conferences with such files range from the late 1980s to the early 1990s. These conferences and meetings are mostly related to the issue of criminal justice and capital punishment. A number of conference and meeting files were assigned publication numbers since they may have been later published. These can be found in Series 2 Subseries 2.
  - American Academy of Psychotherapists, Tenth Annual, Washington, DC, 1965 October 16-1965 October 17 (Box 1 (7-Conferences and Meetings), Folder 1)
  - Attorney General's Conference: "Criminal Justice: Approaches to Reform", 1988 May 20 (Box 1 (7-Conferences and Meetings), Folder 2)
  - Brochures, 1947-1966 (Box 1 (7-Conferences and Meetings), Folder 3)
  - Brochures, 1975-1986 (Box 1 (7-Conferences and Meetings), Folder 4)
  - Claremont Institute, "The Ambiguous Legacy of the Enlightenment", Claremont, CA, 1990 January 25-1990 January 27 (Box 1 (7-Conferences and Meetings), Folder 5)
  - Dickinson School of Law, "The Death Penalty in America: The Debate Rages On", Carlisle, PA, 1991 April 29 (Box 1 (7-Conferences and Meetings), Folder 6)
  - International Conference on Justice in Punishment, Israel, 1988 (Box 1 (7-Conferences and Meetings), Folder 7)